Finding Aid for Robert Kirby Winters Papers, 1923-1986
Bentley Historical Library, University of Michigan
Robert Kirby Winters Papers
1923-1986
Winters, Robert Kirby, 1902-
88280 Aa 2
Specialist in the area of international forestry with the U. S. Forest Service. Personal and professional files; also publications, speeches, and other writings; and photographs.
2.5 linear feet
Bentley Historical Library, University of Michigan
The collection was the gift of Robert K. Winters (donor no. 7447 ) and came to the library in May 1987.
The collection is open to research.
Robert K. Winters, born May 11, 1902, in Douglas, Michigan, earned three degrees from the University of Michigan: a Bachelor of Science of Forestry in 1924; a Master of Science of Forestry in 1925; and a Ph.D. in forestry in 1930. Upon completing his education, Winters embarked on a long career with the Forest Service of the United States Department of Agriculture, ending as Director of the International Forestry Division. After his retirement in 1967, Winter's involvement with international forestry did not abate; he continued to serve as international consultant to the Society of American Foresters until 1983.
Winter's career reflected his growing interest in international forestry and his writings reflect his persistent interest in forestry history. As Winter's career unfolded, he filled a variety of positions ranging from Forest Ranger to Regional Director of the Forest Survey, to Director of the International Forestry Division. His positions called on him to fill many roles: liaison between the Forest Service and the War Production Board; researching economic yield and productivity of forests; and training foreign nationals. Winter's service spanned the nation and the world, taking him from New Orleans, to Missoula, to Chittagong, Pakistan, to Washington, D.C. Through it all, Winters saw the importance of sharing knowledge and expertise, hence he devoted much time and energy to international conferences, professional organizations, and education. These interests carried through Winter's retirement, but he also had time to devote to history of forestry. It was at this time Winters researched and wrote The Forest and Man, a history of the world's civilizations and their use of trees.
The Robert K. Winters papers document his career with the Forest Service and reflect his interests in forestry as an international science and the history of forestry. The papers span the years 1923-1986 with the bulk of materials covering Winter's professional interests in a somewhat uneven manner. The strengths of the Winter's papers rest in his travel notes and diaries, his documenting of the formation of the International Union Society of Foresters (IUSF), the materials related to The Forest and Man, and the transcript of his oral history. Winter's duties as liaison officer to the War Production Board, his years as Chief of Central States Economics Research Division, and his service with Forest Products Marketing Research are not well documented by these papers. Similarly Winter's personal life is only thinly documented.
The Winter's papers are arranged in three groups: Personal; Professional; and Publications, Speeches and Writings. Within these groups, materials are arranged in a rough chronological order.
Subjects:
Conservation of natural resources--United States.; Forests and forestry--United States.; United States. Forest Service.
Subjects - Visual Materials:
Agriculture--United States.; Forestry.; Forests.; Lumber industry.; Mexico.; Texas.; Winters, Robert Kirby, 1902-
Genre Terms:
Photographs.
- Personal Papers, 1923-1986
  The Personal papers group comprises less than four linear inches of the collection and contains the transcript of Winter's Oral history. As these recollections reflect Winter's own lucid insights to his career, they should be the starting point for any researcher.
  - Genealogy of Winter's family in America, circa 1975 (Box 1)
  - Oral History of Robert K. Winters, 1986
    - Notes, 1986 (Box 1)
    - Transcript, 1986 (Box 1)
  - Correspondence, 1923-1950 (Box 1)
    (include photo)
  - Correspondence, 1951-1984 (Box 1)
  - Notes/Correspondence toward History of International Agricultural Development, 1976-1978 (Box 1)
  - Notes on American Foresters, 1978-1981 (Box 1)
  - Reminiscences on Forestry during World War II, circa 1978; audio-cassettes (Box 1)
- Professional Papers, 1923-1986
  The Professional papers comprise twenty linear inches and contain bound travel notes on Winter's professional journeys to Europe, Mexico, and in United States forests. Winter's bound diaries describing his months as a timber cruiser and years in Chittagong, Pakistan are in this group. Aside from the materials detailing the formation of the IUSF, the materials on conferences and professional affiliation serve only to indicate the breadth of Winter's activities. Researchers should consult Winter's Professional Biography folder for a quick overview of his career.
  - Professional Biography, 1986 (Box 1)
  - Travel and miscellaneous
    - Timber Cruising in California (Diary), May-September 1923 (Box 1)
    - Travel Notes-Europe, May-September 1930; bound manuscript (Box 1)
    - Travel Notes-Southern Forest Conditions, 1931-1938; 2 volumes (Box 1)
    - Photo Albums-Southern Forest Conditions, 1931-1938; 2 volumes (Box 1)
    - Travel Notes-Texas and Mexico (bound ms), 1935 (Box 1)
      (include photos)
    - Travel Notes-Montana and Idaho, 1939-1942; bound manuscript (Box 2)
    - "U.S. Forest Service Reappraisal,", 1947 (Box 2)
    - "Incentive Payments for Forestry Practices,", 1951 (Box 2)
    - University of Michigan: Semi-centennial of Forestry Education, 1952 (Box 2)
    - Chittagong, Pakistan, 1952-1955
      - Correspondence, 1953-1954 (Box 2)
      - Diary, 1952-1954 (Box 2)
      - Miscellaneous, 1953-1955 (Box 2)
      - Publications re: India, 1954 (Box 2)
    - Training Foreign Nationals
      - General, 1958-1966; 2 folders (Box 2)
      - Soviet Exchange, 1959 (Box 2)
  - Conferences
    - International Forestry Division (IFD), 1962-1981 (Box 2)
    - Food and Agriculture Organization, 1962-1977
      - VIII Conference: Santiago, Chile, 1962 (Box 2)
      - Rome, 1962-1964 (Box 2)
      - North American Forestry Session: Washington, D.C., 1965 (Box 2)
      - Committee on Forest Development in Tropics, 1967 (Box 2)
      - Correspondence, 1976-1979 (Box 2)
    - International Union Forestry Research Organizations (TUFRO), 1974-1981
      - Forest History Section, 1974-1979 (Box 2)
      - XVI World Congress, Oslo, 1976 (Box 2)
      - Symposium, Hamburg, 1979 (Box 2)
      - XVII World Congress, Kyoto, 1981 (Box 2)
    - World Forestry Congresses, 1965-1972
      - VI Madrid, 1965-1966 (Box 2)
      - VII Buenos Aires, 1970-1972 (Box 2)
  - Professional Affiliations, 1968-1983
    - International Union Society of Foresters, 1968-1985; 3 folders (Box 2)
    - Society of American Foresters
      - Committee on World Forestry, 1968-1979; 2 folders (Box 2)
      - Correspondence, 1969-1979 (Box 2)
      - Terminology Committee, 1972-1981 (Box 2)
      - Renewable Resources Foundation, 1977-1983 (Box 2)
- Publications, Speeches, and Writings, 1928-1983
  The Publications, Speeches, and Writings series rounds out the collection. This group consists primarily of material Winter's pulled together after his retirement. Aside from correspondence dealing with the book The Forest and Man, most of the material in this group consists of articles, manuscripts, and notes.
  - Bibliography, 1981 (Box 3)
  - "The Forest Reserves in Congress, 1891-1897", 1928 (Box 3)
  - "Federal/Legislation on Public Domain and Forest Conservation,", 1930 (Box 3)
  - Miscellaneous Speeches, 1931-1948 (Box 3)
  - Fifty Years of Forestry in the U.S.A. (book), 1950 (Box 3)
  - The Forest and Man (book), (published 1974), 1961-1979
    - Africa Travel Notes, 1973; audiocassettes (Box 3)
    - Expenses, 1973-1979 (Box 3)
    - Notes and Correspondence, 1961-1978; 5 folders (Box 3)
  - "How Forestry became part of FAO,", 1970-1971 (Box 3)
  - Terminology of Forest Science Technology Practice and Products (book expedited by Winters), 1971 (Box 3)
  - "Forest" article in Encyclopedia Americana, 1969-1971 (Box 3)
  - "World Forestry" chapter in Introduction to Forestry, 1973-1983 (Box 3)
  - "Forestry in India,", 1975 (Box 3)
  - "International Forestry in U.S.D.A.,", 1979-1981 (Box 3)
  - "History of Tropical Forests,", 1980 (Box 3)
  - Journal of Forestry World Forestry page articles, 1970-1980 (Box 3)